Chris: So, what is a Deployment strategy?
A ‘deployment strategy’ is a process to
change or upgrade a software product.
One of the aims of a ‘deployment strategy’, is to
release a new version without downtime, so that
the user is free to continue using the product.
One of the more common strategies is the
‘blue-green’ deployment strategy but there are
several different strategies that can be used
Let’s have a look at these
in a little more detail.
Leah: Basic deployment is fast,
simple, and cost-effective.
To create a new version, it does a full
update of the product in the environment
simultaneously, This process makes it
vulnerable, more difficult to update, and this
strategy would make it harder to rollback.
It carries the highest risk
and would be unsuitable for
business-critical products or services.
Chris: The blue-green deployment
strategy would have two versions of
a software product at the same time.
The new ‘blue’ version goes through testing
and evaluation while the user continues
to use the stable ‘green’ version.
The user will be switched to the
‘blue’ version when it is ready.
This is a good strategy to use, as
if there is a problem, it can be
switched back to the ‘green’ version.
One way to think of this is how it would look in
a source [version] code control environment such
as ‘Git’ or ‘GitHub’, there would be a ‘Staging
branch’ which would be the ‘blue’ version, and a
Master branch which would be the ‘green’ version.
Leah: Multi-service deployments are
also simple, fast, cheap but are not
as risky as a ‘basic deployment’.
This is due to it being used for products that
have service or version dependencies, meaning
they will only work if they are up to date.
In a multi-service deployment, all
the parts of the software are kept
separately, but updated at the same time.
This type of deployment is,
however, slow to rollback and can be
difficult to manage, test and verify.
Chris: Rather than doing a ‘full update’
at each deployment, a rolling deployment
updates an ‘instance’ of the previous
version of the software product.
It will wait until it is ready before
redirecting users to the new version,
therefore eliminating downtime.
If there is an issue such as a bug, the rolling
deployment can be stopped, so is easy to rollback.
Leah: A canary deployment is used to test
a ‘new version’ of a software product
and can be easily rolled back to the
‘previous version’ if there is an issue.
This strategy is used within both
‘blue-green’ and ‘A/B testing’.
A new version [the canary] is tested
before the old instances are replaced.
If it fails the readiness test, then the
‘canary instance’ is removed, and the
deployment would automatically be rolled back.
A ‘canary release’ has the lowest
risk due to its element of control.
Chris: An alternative strategy is to use A/B
testing which is also known as ‘A/B versions’ This
is where both versions are active at the same time
with different groups of users on each version.
It can be used to test ‘interface
changes’ and ‘features’ to get ‘user
feedback’ and be used for ‘verification’.
This strategy differs to the other
deployment strategies as its focus is
on ‘experimentation and exploration’.
A/B testing is more about testing multiple ideas,
rather than deploying one specific tested idea.